[Music]
and welcome back to another segment of
boldly mill I'm Rachel Morrison and I'm
Michael Sean Conaway and I have the
great pleasure of bringing you a
conversation with my good friend Daniel
Martin Berger he is a guy who spends a
lot of time on global and global
catastrophic risks something that will
have you think for a while and I'm sure
this conversation will give us a new
perspective on the things that we're
dealing with on a day to day basis and
really as we look forward into the
future what are the some of the things
that are important for us to look
towards Daniel welcome really great to
have you here today
thanks for having me let's just start
off with where you are you know for all
of us the pandemic has caused some some
dramatic and large shifts in life but I
find that that extra just that's
different for everybody in their worlds
how is your world been altered or
changed are there things that have
changed the levels of importance and
urgency for you yeah what's what's going
on over there for you it's interesting
having been communicating with people
about the risk of large-scale global
catastrophes for a long time versus
being in one that is happening in terms
of people's general ability to feel the
reality of it and at this point the
actual risk from the virus itself is
relatively small compared to the risk of
our responses to the virus so when we're
talking about things like shutting down
travel which makes sense if there's a
viral transmission thing but in ways
that don't protect food supply issues
and then damaging the pesticides getting
to northern Africa and parts the Middle
East so locusts take over the food and
restaurants not being able to be the
major importers of food and not having
other supply chain possibilities and so
you know damaging the food supply for
two billion people is a bigger deal then
the viruses itself in terms of actual
risk to life so is the in
authoritarian ISM of states breakdown of
international alliances increase in
state-based and corporate based
surveillance capabilities escalation
pathways towards violence so you know
we're in a the situation was like Co vid
was just a big enough thing that it was
able to set off a cascade of things that
were all that would have been set off by
something right because there was all
these systemic fragilities and so now
people's relationship to the topic of
global catastrophic risk is different
yeah and and you know how does that does
that alter your work at all you've just
been working on the things you've been
working on is there any change of focus
or change of urgency or anything for you
right now yeah I mean there's there are
a lot more people who are more ready to
take the conversation seriously so
there's a lot of things that have
accelerated for us there's also a lot of
things that have to happen on relatively
quick timelines where they reach points
of irreversibility so there's a lot in
my focus and work that has happened
because of that
responding to kovat is intelligible
right and I'm way more than responding
to global ecological crisis or AI risk
or anything else was its intelligible in
a different way and eminence right and
timely and having government funds
allocated to it and all the new cycles
and things like that and so insofar as
responding to Kove it also means
responding to the second-order effects
associated with Co vid there are a lot
more institutional conversations
happening that are at least kind of
thinking about some things a little bit
better far from adequate so at the same
time I would say that the general
information ecology has gotten much much
worse I mean it was already completely
fragmented but and I would say one of
the things it is
most concerning to me and we're doing
some work towards trying to help with
this is the mismatch between the actual
complexity of the problems facing the
world and the complexity that most
people can actually process on their own
so most people want relatively simple
narratives and so that you see this in
bipartisan politics is that they want
some kind of who the good guys are and
who the bad guys are and they either
want that the General Authorities are
generally good and the virus is really
serious and we should kind of listen to
the authorities and stay home and or the
General Authorities are probably bad and
this is a attempt to take all our civil
liberties away and the virus is probably
exaggerated and the nuance of like well
the virus is serious and there are real
serious responses that need to happen
there's also a lot of predatory
opportunism that various power actors
have there's a distribution of the
goodness and badness of authorities
towards different goals the the actual
reality of it is just much more fucking
nuanced and complex and not a simple
narrative arc and then when it comes to
the science of like so how what is the
actual case fatality rate is this just a
flu is it more serious than the flu the
epidemiology is not totally trivial
right to actually understand wait are we
doing background tests on non
symptomatic people and is an
immunological assay of the right kind
and does it what are the false positives
and negatives and and then people will
start talking about the association of
5-g or maybe it's not really a virus
it's an exosome well most people don't
have enough molecular biology to be able
to answer that and so then whoever it is
it starts trending on Facebook because
it hits some emotional tropes ends up
being what gets shared and echo-chamber
effective and it's emotional and it's
consequential and people are actually
spending more time trying to sense make
while coming up with worse answers and
then also wanting to act on AI wanting
to take their guns and go out in front
of the protest building or wanting to
get Facebook and Google to shut down all
news of those types of those people
don't do that
which are all basically escalations
towards violence of different types all
based on wrong information and theirs is
their I mean this is the economy the
information ecology so damaged that
there's little or no hope of actually
getting good information right now I
think that what it takes to get
actionable intelligence to get enough
information that your action on it will
actually be appropriate action is a
higher level of capacity and discipline
than most people have yeah and that's
the tricky thing yeah and we have to
have trust somewhere then we're gonna
have to trust we're gonna have to if we
can't do it for ourselves and either we
have go with an understanding that we're
not going to ever have good sense making
or we have to trust somebody's analysis
we have to trust our own discernment
capacity to know who we trust right like
this is true in personal relationships
if you trusted somebody and got hurt
because they embezzled from you or
cheated on you or whatever it is there's
a deeper question around why did you
trust them if they were not actually
trustworthy which is trusting your own
capacity for discernment and their it
might be trustworthiness of intent but
also trustworthiness of capacity and
sense-making
so to the degree that I want to
cognitively offload some of the
complexity to someone else I'm still
ultimately responsible for what I
believe in the consequence of my actions
based on those beliefs if they're wrong
or right and so what level of
understanding do I need when experts in
the field disagree to even decide where
I trust well and I think another
question to be asking around that is how
can we discern a person's ability to
articulate the complexity as an absolute
truth or a part of our truth that we can
put into our baskets then later
synthesized and not blindly agree
because of the poetic feelings I believe
that the emotional pole
that it allows me to feel and sometimes
you know I I have to admit that and
these conscious quote-unquote conscious
conversations around what's happening to
these little pandemics people want to be
agreeable with someone who has that
ability to articulate complexities
mostly for the sake of because it allows
them to have some sort of validity and
making them feel smarter or more
included in that narrative which is
really not the reason why you would want
to agree to someone's material in the
first place and then what happens is we
get a lot of blind knowledge nodding and
agreeably to what's happening for
somebody and then that becomes the
general narrative that leads into maybe
sometimes a misled group of people
taking unreasonable action in the world
and you know we have enough of those
clusters going around and then we have
everybody going in every which way
direction with a spoon fed and self
imposed righteousness attached to it in
some way and so I'm curious how can we
build our capacities better to bring a
higher level of balance into what it is
that we can collectively do and pose the
the question to even have a question
about the information that we're having
as we continue this this journey
together yeah you as to how question and
there's some very basic things that will
create some traction it's not the whole
answer but basic things first I'll say
something about agreeableness since you
mentioned that that the spirit of good
sense making of good epistemology is the
earnest desire to know and so bias of
any kind is the enemy of science or
epistemology or or sense making right
agreeableness and disagreeableness are
both biases
and their relational biases to relate in
a particular way with the person but
that also means relating with their
information in a way that predisposes a
particular kind of relationship to that
information
independent of what the actual truth of
it is so there are people who like to be
disagreeable who will just figure out
how to devil's advocate you no matter
what that's not that useful right
because that's a lot of waste of time
and energy if what you're saying is
actually true and they should and if
they didn't have that bias they'd be
like oh yeah that actually makes sense
and agree ability similarly leads to
[Music]
echo chambers and people not actually
thinking and so I really like for people
to not have either of those biases as
much as possible and to separate their
desire to have effective relationships
with people and their desire to think a
particular thing about a particular
topic so I can disagree with you well
totally respecting you and having a good
relationship and if I can't and fuck us
both because we're super immature right
and so it's important in a healthy
relationship that I can actually say
well I can see why you came to that that
like I can there's a lot in that that is
interesting I come to a different take
right they disagree let me tell you how
where I'm coming from but I'm not
actually having any abrasiveness
relationally between us because I'm not
identifying with my views and even when
I disagree I'm not sure that I'll be
right right I'm saying my current
assessment come to a different place
than yours but I'm giving you the
benefit of the doubt enough then staying
in conversation with you right and maybe
your perception will change and maybe
mine mother so that's something on the
bias of agreeableness and
disagreeableness on some specific house
before agreeing or disagreeing with
someone's perspective you want to make
sure that you can steal man their
perspective well right straw man
means that you rephrase the other
person's argument but in a kind of
weakened or caricature version that sets
up your ability to take it out it's a
classic tool of rhetoric and debate
right steel matting is the opposite it's
actually trying to make their argument
even better than they made it trying to
really understand the essence of it and
construct it and even more clear and
profound and concise and compelling way
and so especially if there are a few
competing perspectives and you can steal
man all of them before coming to your
own that's a really good process so you
can be like okay I see these two viral
adjusts disagreeing on viral origin it's
lab mate or it's not lab mate do I
understand the argument well enough to
actually recreate their argument clearly
where they'd be like oh yes you got it
before I agree or disagree or am i
agreeing or disagreeing without actually
really understanding what that nature
paper said or why that Nobel Prize
winner said that thing because it
emotionally hits the biased I resonate
with is that I kind of like the
conspiratorial biowarfare thing versus I
kind of don't like that and if you don't
understand it well enough to steal man
both sides you shouldn't have a strong
perspective you should just say I don't
know and just sit in the unknowing and
say if I want to know enough I have to
study but to have a strong belief where
I don't understand the topic is much
worse than just saying I don't know like
that's that's the best way to make a
jackass out of myself so I would rather
say if I want to know enough what does
it take to actually be able to know
where people who have more expertise
than me disagree and there's a bunch of
humility that comes in like you know I
have a pretty good science background
but when I see two biologists who are
both eminent who spent 30 years just
studying that topic could disagree I'm
like I'm not gonna learn everything they
know in a hurry how the fuck would I
even think I have a chance of
understanding well possibly possibly
because they might have became eminent
because there are certain biases they do
ride that give that makes
and hypotheses and they explore them and
so maybe become because I don't know the
space as well I have more epistemic
flexibility that if I really try to
understand their arguments and steal men
them
I can see something between them with
more episode and flexibility I'd be the
only hope I would have of reconciling
that at all right but that actually ends
up working which is pretty amazing
I want to just mark what you said there
Doug and I remember early my early Zen
training life being told dull I don't
know is probably the wisest thing we
could say about anything so that that
really resonates but the I think that's
I think that I think we we kind of feel
like we must know or must have an
opinion especially about this kovat
thing it seems that and then maybe
that's part of the the part of the the
polemic of info war in generals it makes
us feel like we have to pick a side and
that I don't know means that maybe we
don't care or something like that I
think that maybe it's a it's a higher
order of answer period and then the
second thing I got on that Daniel is it
if I want to know it requires an
investment so it has to be important to
me and so that means there's going to be
whole categories of since making them
maybe I don't engage in and and I do
have big pieces of things that I don't
know about and then in regards to
something that I may be wanting to put
into the world or some action I might
want to take it might be really really
important for me to invest the time to
know in the way you're talking about so
I think that's really valuable a
valuable piece if I want to get buff or
I want to learn to paint well or I want
to play the piano there's a difference
between I want that and I can actually
do it well which is called a shit ton of
training yeah and so coming to
understand biology and biology and
epidemiology and coming to understand
political science and economic theory
well are not trivial right and
especially to try to have some grand
narratives that synthesize knowing all
of those things together now if I say I
don't know it could be seen as I don't
care I generally take it and sometimes
that is right someone doesn't
because they really don't give a shit
but it can also be that you care more I
actually care so much that I'm not
willing to have false confidence that
biases me because once I start to have I
think I know now I just have
confirmation bias where I look for
things that confirm that and throw out
the other things and surround myself
with people that agree with me and if I
really care that's the worst thing I
could do I ruined my ability to be
connected to reality at that point
instead wanting to just get confirmation
of a particular type of social signal
from a particular audience that will
confirm that for me and so I'd much
rather be able to say I really care and
I really don't know and that's
uncomfortable it's funny it's you said
that I just thought of some kind of the
of the you know the notion that
democracy doesn't work without a
well-informed public it seems like I
don't know may actually be one of the
best states of inform that you could be
honest about it's the ending of the
possibility of a real angry it's the
beginning of the possibility of coming
to know anything in a worthwhile way
yeah great now you know like so so
obviously here we are in the state we're
dealing with political realities
economic realities in some case health
health realities that are very
disruptive can I say one more thing to
Rachel's question on the how just one
baby a simple simple thing that I'll
pick back up on the other than good if
there's something you're starting to
think is probably true where there is
division and belief around it find some
people who are really smart who disagree
with you and talk to them and ideally
people who know the field better than
you do and notice one see can I steal
man their arguments do they have some
data I don't and also notice your own
bias am i trying to discredit them
instantly
am I trying to identify their cognitive
biases and say they're conspiracy
theorists are there a standard model or
whatever it is so that I don't have to
take seriously the fact that they might
be fucking up my confidence right now oh
great yeah so considering the impact
that this pandemic has had on us and
know obviously there's a health
impact for some people there's certainly
economic and you know political impacts
and then an uncertain future impacts is
is really I think one place that that
many of us are standing especially as we
starting to look out there like six
months or a year or two years three
years like you know in an attempt to
either a predict the future which I you
know we're not a very big fan of but
when you actually start looking at you
know being generative with your ideas
about the future and what might be a
better state you know what what do you
kind of have to offer us and in terms of
like you know where are we at now and
and what is some of the things that that
that are some of the forces that are at
work at defining what our near-term
future might look like six 12 18 months
and then really what are some of the
alterations that are that there's actors
out there pushing on us and then maybe
some things that you're thinking of or
we might think of that would be a
desirable state to move towards after
this this pandemic or after this period
of disruption if we just think about the
pandemic and the whole conversation
around return to normal a lot of things
have been really profoundly damaged
already and and I don't just mean people
who died right and family members and
emotions and those who depended on them
financially and all of those things oh
that's a big deal but the number of
small businesses that closed the small
businesses go out of business for
something like this it's a lot like
cutting down an old-growth forest you
just can't regrow quickly you can fail a
business that has small margins much
faster than you can regrow a bunch of
new ones now huge businesses can come in
who have war chests and start to buy up
that space so that represents you know
one of the most severe consolidation of
wealth possibilities that we've ever
seen similarly when the market crashes
and all of the real infrastructural
value stocks are really cheap so those
who have a bunch of liquid
can buy them all up that's again massive
consolidation of wealth on what was
already an unsustainable economic
inequality we see that the GDP went down
but the debt went up and we already had
more of our GDP debt servicing than was
sustainable and so that represents
basically a you know a fatal blow to an
already mostly dead system what happens
from that and then we start to look at
the damage that's happened to the EU as
a system and what that means for Eurasia
and the belt and road initiative and you
know so many things like that we start
to look at food supply chains so if we
just got let's say that we got a magical
vaccine tomorrow we won't but let's say
we did we'd be returning into a world
that was radically damaged not by the
virus but by all of the second third
order effects so if we want to return to
a not really damaged world we have to
fix not just the virus but fix those
other things and what it takes to fix
those would require a level of people
understanding them so would require
better sense making and way the fuck
better coordination ie governance at
both you know nation-state levels
between public and private sector and
internationally and if we got that we
could make it much much much better
right because those are those would be
significant changes to the core
civilization systems so we will come out
of this different and it will either be
meaningfully worse or meaningfully
better in terms of the overall health
and integrity of the global Commons and
systems and then looking out beyond that
time or looking at is that is this this
thing that I mean I just want my really
clear flat simple question is this is
this an opportunity for systems upgrades
or championing things that might be of
long-term benefit to humanity and the
planet yes of course
you mentioned when we were talking
earlier about you know the frame that
some people are holding of the kind of
pause that this is right well the most
powerful actors in the world not only
don't have a pause they've increased
their activity many fold right the
Kremlin and the CCP and the DNC and the
GOP they're not paused right they're
fucking power grabbing like crazy and
trying to advance their agendas and
doing so with really asymmetric
information capabilities and capital
capabilities and team capabilities and
actuation capabilities so anyone who
feels like it's a great pause that also
says where you are in the food chain
kind of what's influencing the world so
I think there's a lot of things that are
being advanced that and when you mention
opportunity that some people are seeing
as opportunities to advance their
personal interests in ways they're bad
for the interests of others are the
whole so there are some people who for
whatever reason really believe in or
like or are aesthetically attracted to
authoritarian type structures so when
you see you know the President of the
Philippines when it was time for
quarantine just so happily taken say yes
shoot people who are violating
quarantine it just appeals to a
sensibility like his to take
authoritarian measures of those kinds so
and in more technologically advanced
countries those same people are looking
at implementing massive thermal scans
and AI drone type capabilities and
surveillance capabilities and how much
is just their own personal economic
incentive associated being the major you
know funders or or owners of those
companies and those technologies versus
is it aligned with political agendas or
ideological agendas so there's a lot of
people pursuing opportunities but that
are not the opportunities that we would
say create the highest quality of life
for
everybody in a good in in what I would
call a good sense making frame now there
are some people doing things that are
authentically really interesting right
now and it could move things in the
right direction but they are not they
don't have as much resource they aren't
as well coordinated so as the food
supply chains break this is a real
interesting one right so we see the
coaling which is this very funny
sanitized term right : of all the
chickens and the pigs and like that and
burying the potatoes and pouring down
the drain all the milk
just as many people exist that need to
eat like what the fuck why are we
destroying all the supply when there's
just as much aggregate demand it's just
the demand used to go to McDonald's
right it used to go to a few major
distribution centers when those
distribution centers can't get it and
you're operating on relatively tighter
margins then the supply side is like
well we can't keep paying for these pigs
or these chickens if we can't sell stuff
so it's actually cheaper for us to just
kill them and destroy them but then all
the people still need food and like
that's just a supply chain issue right
that's a supply intelligence so just can
we get the supply to the demand through
a different route well the longer the
route is the easy the more steps there
are they can damage it so the movement
to say well we should actually have food
supply be more distributed and more
local oh and by the way if it's more
local there won't be factory farms
because nobody wants to be around a
factory farm because they're fucking
horrible and so you have to put them
somewhere far away and then of course
that means it's centralized shipping to
everywhere else so does that mean that
we can get better Ethical Treatment of
Animals better environmental care better
health for the people and better
robustness and resiliency of the food
supply grid simultaneously yeah totally
that should happen right and there's
some totally inadequate but some
movements happening in that direction
this is an interesting one because this
is something where like anyone can
engage to some degree right you can just
say I'm gonna do a home garden right and
that's engaging to some degree or I'm
gonna help a community garden in our air
I'm gonna help our small towns start
working on local resilience like can we
get a couple people to start engaging in
growing stuff for this region as opposed
to everything being based on import and
export and so there's like there's real
local shit you can do to engage in that
at the same time there's stuff that some
people need to do to sake who have real
supply chain capabilities and enough
money to front the costs to be able to
you know meet the supply and demand
where it's at
so for every one of the places where it
could go really bad there's an
opportunity right the kids not being at
school and the combination of them
getting way more screen addiction as a
result of more domestic abuse happening
as a result of damage happening in their
social development like that's pretty
bad actually when you think about what
that means for a generation is pretty
bad but the opportunity to say fuck
let's we have to fix that and while
we're fixing it let's just kind of
rethink education from scratch and how
do we if we were gonna be delivering
education not to the legacy system how
would we do it that's a pretty awesome
opportunity a bunch of jobs go away and
we realize wow there was a bunch of jobs
that were really just bullshit jobs
right like there were just make work
kind of jobs well if those people can't
feed their families they don't care
because like it was meeting some need
but we also get to say can we start to
rethink our like what productive and
meaningful work and how people get there
you know finances Medora so I'd say if
you go across the sector's just take
health care take you know pick every
sector and say what are the risks in
this space and what harm has already
happened and associated with that to
solve the harm to prevent the risks and
to make it better what would better look
like what are the opportunities in that
space that's a valuable thought process
great so let's think about you know
somebody might be watching this this
video right now Dan Yellin and you know
that there may be theirs they've they've
kind of got some of the harm in for work
has done to our information ecology and
they have a sense that I think that it's
difficult to make sense but they have a
longing or like just a general feeling
if they want to be of service you know
right now no how did that how do they
get started I mean like like and we've
talked we're talking you know through
the years a lot about consciousness what
we mean by raising consciousness but
they're like what are what are some of
those things right now this is a moment
where we get to retake we get to take
stock where our lives and think about
how we might reconstitute ourselves
differently than than before you know
what are some of the things that that we
can look to what are the steps that we
might be able to take to be able to
participate meaningfully in a world that
works better or ultimately a thriving
room and pause because I know I know
statistically that whatever I say even
if it is inspiring won't make it through
people's memory after they scroll
Facebook or Instagram the first time or
get on a phone called it's stressful and
so inspiration that isn't gonna last
through a bunch of hyper normal stimuli
not worth so much so if I wanted to say
what could people do and they would feel
inspired after this but then they would
lose it the first thing I want to say is
well and what could you do to not lose
it what could you do to stay engaged in
a conversation that would keep orienting
you in the right direction so that's
kind of meta to the specific thing to do
but it's how to be engaged in a way that
will keep engaging you so I would say if
I had to pick one thing that would have
people do is figure out how to engage
more often with people and content that
are actively doing things that you find
inspiring that will orient your
attention continuously that way because
whether it's Facebook or your family or
your job or your kids or whatever it is
there will be a lot of things that are
orienting you in other directions and
being oriented to what is it that I feel
really
lately called you know which very much
might be your kids but from a different
frame right what is that I feel most
called to engage in I would say figure
out how to engage and this is like this
is the purpose of church right or the
Sangha was that you kind of need to keep
coming back and having some regular
community reminder because humans are
social primates and the thing that
affects us more than anything is who
were around and I know that's why you
know in addition to this festival you're
working on putting out more content so
people can have a regular kind of
exposure
that's the meta thing I would say I can
now say some more specific things if you
want yeah yeah what do you see
so somebody listening to this is a
online marketer and somebody's an
accountant and someone's a construction
worker and somebody is a farmer and
somebody's a trust fund kid and
somebody's an Instagram model they can't
all do the same thing right like they
have very different skills very
different knowledge very different
calling and so if I start saying okay
well here's what we do to restructure
global finance well which of those
people will that be the really relevant
thing for so it's hard to try to speak
to a very general audience in that way
so what I would say is whatever level of
expertise you have and whatever kind of
areas of calling there is definitely
useful shit you can do if you feel
called to do useful things and if you
want to do useful things that more scale
which is totally not the only thing to
do because there's a lot of people who
for ego reasons want to think about
scale while totally neglecting
everything around them and so much so
many problems would be better if people
were just not neglecting what was around
them then we wouldn't all be depending
upon some scaled things solving all of
our problems which is what leads to a
few companies and organizations running
the whole world who aren't close enough
to possibly have the optics to know how
to be helpful so might be like well I'm
taking care of homeless dogs in my city
this doesn't address homeless dogs
all cities or all animals but it fucking
addresses these ones right and if I can
after I do that start to put out here's
what we did that was helpful in our city
for other cities right like those are
good steps so right now with Cova
there's a lot of people who are lonely
enough that they're killing themselves
do you and some of them will end up
being people that you find out about
that you knew right or who are just
older people were just really suffering
so you don't have to have any very
specialized knowledge or any high
profile sense-making to be able to see
where there's need and reach out and be
responsive to it
so that's a huge thing to the degree
that you feel called to things that are
systemic question it actually because
it's probably wrong I'm saying this is
someone who's systemically focused but
partly that is just because we're not
getting local news we're getting global
news and so our attention is being
bombarded by things that aren't actually
in the world that we're in and that are
at a scale that we really can't fucking
do anything about or even know how to
make sense about so it mostly just that
is the narrative warfare at a high level
that's trying to get our beliefs so we
vote and purchase and retweet in a
particular way to support those who are
acting at that scale with specific types
of agendas and your desire to have a
strong opinion and be able to do some
online warrior shit is largely some
stronger forces having co-opted you into
being a soldier for something you don't
even understand
well I'm it so it's often a distraction
tactic actually and then an avoidance
tactic that many of us use to not
actually do the work onward for us at a
very very local level that internal
level the home level the direct
community level and we distract
ourselves with so many of these
narratives it can be avoidance it can be
you know grandiose gratification it can
be simply the addictive I can't not know
right
whatever can be the hyper normal
stimulus of OSHA deletes our drinking
baby blood I have to know about that
right because it's like it designed to
hit all of the big the stuff that's
gonna light somebody's need to know up
but there will be some people who are
supposed to do things at a beyond
regional level and scope and then it's
if you feel really clearly called there
what do you have to study to be able to
understand the problem space well enough
to understand the solutions well enough
to implement stuff if you are wanting to
help not just with community gardens in
your area but with food supply so that
millions of pigs don't need to be
slaughtered one can you even learn what
you would need to in time right just
like reality check that and to the
extent that you already have a supply
chain company or whatever and you think
maybe you could then it's like okay who
are the experts you can bring in right
away who are the and especially ones
that have dissenting opinions where you
again get to ask them the question steel
men them come to understand it so that
you make sure that you understand the
problem space well to craft solutions
that make sense so that when you act on
it you're acting effectively to the
degree that people feel called to act at
more scale it's very much like lifting
more weight or playing more advanced
piano pieces there's more training
involved it well said because then we
have to have the capacity to do the
steel Manning and that takes time
complexity more complexity yeah if I'm
if I'm doing a local community garden
there will be economics involved who
buys the piece of land whatever but I
don't need to understand dark pools and
complex financial instruments to do it
in the way that I do if I'm trying to
figure out what's happening with the
global economic stimulus right and so
there is just going to be at scale
inherently more things included in the
scale that means more complexity well
what's so great about complexity even
though it can get pretty vast pretty
quickly is that it lends a wonderful
invitation for collaboration and you
can't solve it I'm yeah but I and I do
think that one of things that we do
skipper
a lot and I think Rachel I'm thinking
what you just said is like like when you
can collaborate in a local level you can
actually coordinate enough people to
have enough range of opinions and views
and capacities and capabilities it it
can be difficult but it's you know
organizing a hundred people is very
different than than 4,000 or 5,000 which
is very very different than 300 million
or a billion and I think a lot of times
especially and a lot of our our world in
our movement is we talk in these really
grand things and then we don't even do
organizing in levels of 10 or 20 or 30
we're the big but not actually engaging
them that the local there's a very
important part of the classically
left-right conversation the left-right
was supposed to be a healthy dialectic
between values that were all important
that in the like steel man different
perspectives right through this
dialectic between rights and
responsibilities between individual and
relationships rather that dialectic
would happen not supposed to be a
warfare but you have to balance rights
and responsibilities in the right way
and either one of them on their own
without balance and ZUP becoming
pathological so if people have rights
and they don't have attendant
responsibilities right so you're raising
kids they have there's a right that they
have to expect that their parents are
gonna feed them and their parents start
as they have capability progressively
they start being involved in helping
wash the dishes and do chores there's
some responsibilities associated with
that that teaches them how to be a
healthy person an effective person in
the world cuz that's going to be the
case in the world right do I have a we
start talking about everyone should have
universal healthcare as a right awesome
who pays for it who pays the doctors and
the nurses and the hospitals and the
diagnostics and builds the MRI machines
now let's start really well the rich
wait okay let's just run all of the
channels of
so whose money is taken by force backed
up by guns right which is ultimately
what law is is a monopoly of violence
and how does that make sense and what
types of incentives does that create an
anti incentives and just you have to
really think through the whole rights
and responsibilities thing it's one of
the reason democracies fail faster than
monarchies it generally is and faster
than Republic's is people will vote
themselves rights that they aren't
willing to take the responsibility to
implement and so then basically everyone
is a child right in their consciousness
and that doesn't work similarly if
people are responsible for something and
they don't have the attendant rights
associated that's some kind of servitude
or slavery right so it's important that
those things be balanced and so the
right side is if I want to operate a
larger scale and have people be
interested in what I have to say there I
kind of have to earn that right if I
want to have like having people listen
to what I have to say is a like it's a
there's a privilege that's associated
with that but I did I don't have the
right to it without the responsibility
that I had to take first to offer things
of value so one of the things I would
say about scale is you earn it you earn
operating at scale if that's your
calling and it shouldn't be most
people's by doing a good job at smaller
skills great sensible makes sense I
think that's a thing it's funny it's
like um we you know we we all the time
start thinking that maybe we have an
idea for large solutions at scale and I
know for myself it's like the it's
taking me years to actually learn to
slow down enough to even ask what I mean
when I think I have an idea for a
solution scale and you know like the the
process of actually examining the
underlying assumptions and and the and
the just huge amount of no data like no
proof no data pieces of kind of if you
will imagination without a relationship
to okay I've imagined something now I
need to go check out and and find out if
that works now if we're an entrepreneur
we
say hey I imagine having the the most
badass music app ever I'm not gonna get
a I'm not gonna walk up to an investor
and say hey give me a hundred million
dollars I'm the most badass music a
pepper like I say great here's $1,000 go
do something or here's $100,000 go do
something show to me that you can in a
very small level making something badass
a bow I think when we start looking at
you know wanting to alter the the
systems in which the world operates we
have that kind of naivete like we're
gonna likes if somebody just give me the
authority to say how it's gonna be mad I
could just fix all of this stuff really
really quick and I mean that that's I
think that's we would agree that's
that's that naivete that ends up making
decisions that fuck up shit worse than
it was fucked up before we made those
decisions and yet there needs to be some
kind of lattice worth of framework for
us to begin to understand how to try out
ideas you know and and and not the old
idea is not the you know the past 200
years of retreaded ideas over and over
again but and there has to be a way for
us to begin to think new thoughts and
try new things you know where do we get
the space to do that and how do we carve
that out of what is know as I think we
agree as a crumbling society how do we
not just hold on to the stones of the
things around us and try to keep them
from falling down and still have enough
space to to try to stand up these things
in the world you're saying brings up for
me this dialectic between there's a kind
of hubris or a audacity people will use
those terms to be entrepreneurial and
think you can do something has never
been done but that has to be balanced
with the kind of humility of
understanding why it's never been done
and what attempts have failed by people
that were competent and smart and what
things have you know yeah there's a very
important it it's kind of like when we
were saying if I've got two scientists
who spent 30 years studying a topic and
they disagree how the fuck
I possibly even imagined that I could
come to have a view on it when I'm not
gonna study all they studied well
there's a certain hubris in that but
there's also the humility of I know I
don't know what they know but maybe I
can come to understand how they
constructed the ideas well enough that
by being able to take both of their
positions maybe more flexibly than they
do because maybe they hold their own
position more I can gain some insight so
there's there is a kind of faith in a
possibility right that is almost like
hubris it's a faith and a possibility
that I could do that same as like build
a new thing but if I haven't looked at
so what are what are all the attempts to
try and do that that failed or that
ended up going another way because they
res that was actually the wrong thing to
do then it's just almost guaranteed that
I'll just fail and waste the energy of
the other people who engage given a
cross-section of human beings in
different places and locations obviously
with at least enough for resources to
think about the issue who would like to
improve things on both local levels and
global levels in terms of you know
healthy healthy environment healthy food
healthy lifestyle with a relative amount
of safety without actually having the
the keys to Authority you know you know
in the middle of that sandwich not at
the top is is there is there something
for us to do I mean we obviously have
some kind of desire and passion to to
you know make a difference or evolve
things or set things on a better path
you know it is I guess is like maybe
there is no framework but if there was a
framework you know like what what is it
that has us have the capacity to do that
or is it just allowing the
self-organizing universe to - to do its
do its work and we actually just have to
trust that what we're doing is the right
thing to do or that we are effort itself
adds up to something I mean do you see
where I'm kind of stuck between a rock
and a hard place of this Daniel it
relates to the scale question we asked
earlier you're asking a question at
maximum scale great I'll reframe them
I'll just say that hyperlocal scales for
right now because I can certainly
imagine that better than I can
I mean even at the scale of the
cross-section of who we're talking about
right that's a very huge week it's a
very diverse we that have very different
interests and proclivities and
capacities and access so for me to
answer that generalize the level it'll
be a very generalized answer which I can
do I'll do it but it'll be almost
platitude like okay we'll take that and
then we'll reframe it afterwards after
we see what we see how that that fits
great thank you because it's important
to note if I was talking with the
American retail Association what can we
do and it's the heads of the large
retail businesses we could really talk
through with the things that they're
capable of doing and what their mandates
the shareholders are whatever what could
they actually do we could start to map
out the opportunity space and problem
space if we were talking to the Joint
Chiefs of Staff or the National Security
Council or a local group of farmers we
could answer that right or or the
association of accountants or whatever
it is right but when it's this broad
people don't have a shared sense of what
the desirable world is anything more
than just like a feeling right is it
more libertarian or is it more socialist
yeah they're more different than most
people acknowledge and there's other
projects of what we're doing towards it
is it more kind of permaculture a
low-tech or super high-tech
transhumanist upload my brain to the
cloud like even what is desirable is
thought very very differently and our
levels of understanding of how to
advance towards that plus our
capabilities so I'm just noticing that
there there's kind of baked in frames
and the way we ask those questions that
are worth exploring yeah and I'm just
I'm like you know I just wanted to be in
the kind of presence to the inquiry kind
of moment here and you know you think
you talk about you know and I know you
don't like to wear an impact you talk
about you know impact work or all of
these things that we use to describe
like the things that we're doing but I
think in in general I'm just kind of
confronted with the fact that it's
actually not very well questioned
we'd actually don't we don't say what we
mean by them we don't or at least we
don't have a what have a reliable
definition that could be could be shared
amongst a lot of people but we speak to
a spectrum as if there are real things
yeah and to an evangelical protesting
abortion clinics is doing impact work
and to say certain democratically
oriented people supporting Planned
Parenthood fundraising is impact work
and they're out there two pieces of
impact work equally earnestly motivated
a direct war with each other right and
the same is true about like
environmentalism and climate change work
versus oil worker rights for an oil
Union right and so yeah it's just worth
thinking more precisely about some of
these things we're gonna say no please
to take it to even an even smaller scale
all right okay we've gone to the cross
section to maybe some of these regional
spaces and now very niche environments
but take it to even a smaller scale I'm
curious what are some questions that you
ask yourself before you decide that you
care enough about something to put some
effort into knowing about it growing it
putting your focus to it so that when
people that are listening to this have
their own experience and their own self
inquiry decide if they they care enough
about something like what are those
questions to be asking ourselves at that
time to see if we should be putting our
effort or our attention or our study or
our intelligence or our heart with what
all the things that we can care about
because we can care about all of it in
in very equal ways but to get down to
where we're not just sitting there
taking in all the information but
actually putting out something what are
what are some good questions that we
could be asking ourselves maybe
how are you asking yourself when you
choose to do something yeah it's a good
question it's interesting though though
how that we effects it how different it
is when I if I'm at phases in my life
where I haven't had any projects I was
running and I'm just in an interstitial
place and I'm kind of researching so
it's just with my own bandwidth right
versus initiating a project and now
there's a team so I have way more
bandwidth but I also have way more
output it is expected to be able to keep
paying that team right whether it's a
non-profit or for-profit and to be able
to grow the capacity well all of a
sudden I'm actually getting more
constrained on what we focus on even
though there's more more total capacity
right and this is why they experience it
actually running a business or running a
non-profit where you're responsible for
the finance is a can be a very valuable
learning experience is you start to ask
okay this seems super fascinating but
there are a total of 75,000 hours worth
of activity per day we'd like to do and
we can't do all of it so what things do
I do factoring the opportunity costs of
the other things I'm not going to do
well I'd like to be able to do more
total stuff than we actually have the
bandwidth to do so if I just use all of
our bandwidth doing immediate work we
won't grow our bandwidth we're just
using it so I have to think about how do
I do the things that are immediately
needed and things how do we use our
bandwidth in ways that grow our
bandwidth right that show the
effectiveness of what we're doing in
ways that can grow the team and grow the
the financing the legibility the
whatever so you think about is this a
project we can actually figure out if
we're gonna start researching is this a
project we can actually figure out well
enough to offer differential novel
insights do we have the team capability
to do that and then is this something
that if we had those insights we could
act on do we have the channels to be
able to actuate the things that would be
needed or do we just have those insights
we're just sitting on them
and then the opportunity cost of what
other things am I not doing to do this
thing right so those are types of
frameworks that are very basic but they
can be valuable to think about the
finiteness of time well yeah if your
classic two by two matrix even more
basic let's just say yeah make it even
more basic let's say you're one with two
hands and a life choice to make all
right very basic and a lot of people are
that one person in that one room right
now with just two hands and that one
life choice to make right now and so I'm
curious what questions would they be
asking themselves about what's in each
hand to help them decide on what that
one choice it's cuz and maybe that
choice for them is like that one thing
that they've been kind of putting off
their entire life and this quarantine
moment is that moment for them to
actually make that choice so now the way
you frame that as a rephrasing of what
Michael asked because that one person is
now the one person avatar of the we
which is to everybody because when
people are all different again so I will
now go to the very generalized answer I
said today would and I just want to I
just want to point like we're all very
smart
you know people we've done a lot of
study in letting you just like this is
hard stuff you you you you actually get
things get very undistinguished is again
the same question but actually be
examined it's not very distinct it's
very generalized so let's let's hear the
generalize answers even though it may
not be a very effective answer I think
it's it's worth now at least hearing and
exploring that what we're asking is how
do humans live a meaningful life right
like that's the question you're asking
is how do different humans who want
their life to contribute to the
well-being of the whole in some ways
have their life actually be well engaged
and well used and that is the core of
all religious and spiritual and cultural
and philosophical kinds of inquiries
right so that's why I said what I'm
gonna answer is gonna end up being
pretty general because it's a big fuckin
question and it's a so a few things I
can say the reason I was pointing out
that wait are we trying to end all the
abortion clinics or make abortions
available to everybody is that how to
have my life be able to create impact
impact towards what what is my
fundamental ethical framework of what
good is right how do I make sense if not
just what I think is but what ought and
so to inform what I'm going to do
there's the science II side the sense
making side of what is the forecasting
side of what will be the effect of a
specific action and the ethical side of
what is a good life what is a meaningful
world what what am i wanting to
contribute to realizing that most of the
things that people do actually elicit
counter responses and drive Wars rather
than actually advance anything and then
they drive arms races and escalating
wars and they drive second and
third-order negative effects right and
so we build a cool little communication
app so we can just send these tweets to
each other because that seems really
like it's kind of cool the short thing
and then all of a sudden World War 3 is
being waged over it because the
president is using it news like oh fuck
with it those were big unintended
consequences of the things that we were
doing so so how do we make sense of the
world make sense of what is actually
good and write and think through the
effects of our actions right and then
how do we actually act on those things
in a prioritized way and how do we
increase our capacity to keep doing so
those are I think some reframes of the
underneath the question you're asking if
I was trying to be more precise and so
the main thing I would say is like
there's a there's a development of the
humans there's the engagement of us but
also the development of us so that our
engagement keeps being better guided and
effective right and this is the how do I
know more about what's going on how do I
do a better job at prioritizing how do I
do a better job of communicating and
compelling in effective ways all those
things and how do I make sure that what
I'm doing is actually what's most
meaningful to me and my time isn't just
hijacked by habit addiction fear lack of
courage distraction and other things
right that's one of the that's one of
the biggest ones is what are the things
that are hijacking your attention that
on your deathbed will not be some of
your highlights right that won't be the
like those are the things that I'm
really proud of or feel really grateful
about and how can you become
progressively less hijacked by those
also humans have complex motivation
right I want to make these amazing
things happen in the world why well
because I want to save all these kids
over here why well because I care about
those kids that's true but I also want
the credit of being the guy who did that
because of unresolved kind of wounded
ego insecurities stuff where I want that
particular credit and I think that
chicks will actually dig it and I think
I'll make some money in the process
and it will address the fact that I
never got approval for my parents that's
I'm projecting on whatever right like
motive this complex so typically
whenever someone is doing something
there's like 10 or 15 different reasons
they're actually doing in they're
usually only aware of half of them half
of them are subconscious even to them
and of the ones they're aware of they
usually only admit one or two in the
executive summary of the project
statement and so part of it also in
terms of how to be more effective is to
become more reflective into your own
motives and how to heal the things that
are actually siphoning energy away right
as you grow and heal some of the motives
will become deeper and some will become
less so you want to know which are the
ones that are coming from the deepest
truth of who I am and which are the ones
that are coming from distraction trauma
and security and other stuff
so there's personal development to be
able to have rather than mixed motives
that are doing like two masters issues
where it is more like a laser all
coherent so I think what I just said is
people need if they want to become more
effective they need to study the topics
they want to influence more like if
you're really wanting to help with food
security stuff you better study soil and
agriculture and different types of
agricultural systems and why it went the
way that it went what are the financial
challenges whatever so that you
understand what is the problem space
well enough to come up with good
solutions so you need to kind of
actually study the space you need to
look at what things you can implement
because there's a bunch of stuff you'll
only learn by doing and as you start to
do it you'll learn in the process a
tremendous amount of stuff so what can i
implement with my current capacities so
that as I'm studying more one I'm having
impact now and I'm learning in a
tangible grounded way and how can I both
continuously be reminded of what's most
meaningful to me so that I don't get
distracted and hijacked it hijacked and
how can I be engaged in a kind of
personal development process that makes
my motivation itself clearer and so
those are the questions I would ask
underneath it would give rise to the how
can we do good things and my main answer
would be the easiest way to succeed at
that is to interact with people who are
succeeding at that better more often
you'll be the average of the five people
you spend the most time around all the
proximity is destiny all those types of
statements we are social primates more
than we like to admit and that's why we
spend our time on Facebook and Instagram
just actually scrolling at pictures of
other primates right like that's the
thing that really fucking captures us is
and it's so interesting because what
we're it's like junk food where you
extract the salt fat and sugar and
remove all the nutrients so you maximize
the hyper normal stimuli without any of
the real thing and that's what the
social media thing is is it it maximizes
the likes and pictures and interaction
in total number of people while removing
almost all actual kinds of real contact
and vulnerability that are scary but it
shows the longing for social contact and
then also the way we're influenced by
what we're around so if people want to
actually be doing more interesting
things so in each of those areas how do
I get how do I do the personal
development to have ego and security
stuff get in the way less well who is it
a therapist is it a group of friends
that do inquiry together what is the
process is it a church or a song go like
what can I engage in that will ongoingly
help me structurally built into my life
study what groups you know do it I'm
gonna move into a rationalist house in
Berkeley where I'm around people that
are doing that all the time I'm gonna
create a book study groups or whatever
it is so that I'm actively engaged in
learning things right that are
meaningful if I want to get better at
actualizing the things I know who are
the people that are the most fuckin
productive that I know where I really
respect that and spend time figure out
how to be useful to them because they're
busy right so figure out how to free
more of their time than I'm asking for
and because I want to learn how they
think about the world that makes them so
productive so I would say the thing I
can offer that is most useful to all
this is actually the social hack of
don't think you'll do it just through
iron discipline do it through actually
intentionally doping what you're taking
in through your senses regularly which
is mostly who I'm a little in a space
where I don't want to know the answer to
this next question so I'm gonna I'm
gonna go for it but I am curious what
have you been just kind of OCD wanting
to learn about what's that maybe it's
keeping you up at night like what's the
thing for you and the real real what's
the real thing that you are just hyper
focused on getting as much information
as possible right and what's the one
learning that just blew your mind about
it so far one of the questions that has
been very central in my mind lately is
how do we how to architecture social
systems that do not reward sociopathy
sociopathy narcissism sadism or any
other basically power seeking
dispositions that also are either like
to or are willing to cause harm with the
application of that power underneath so
many of the problems in the world is
that the people who are power seeking
and willing to use power in ways to gain
more power end up being the most
powerful people in the world in defining
the world and the people who care about
the global Commons who don't want to
cause harm and who want power seeking
themselves usually don't get much power
which means that they don't influence
the the the overall dynamics of the
space and it's clear to me that we
definitely go extinct if that stays true
and so this is you know this this is an
old question this is kind of the purpose
of law right the purpose of law is to
collectively define what are the types
of really predatory behaviors we agree
we don't do and we will we will shut
those down but of course throughout time
it's like a civilization will create an
effective legal system and then the
legal and governance system the
government is supposed to make laws that
regulate the very predatory aspects of
of markets and personal advantage
seeking but then that means that the
main goal of those predatory markets is
to get around or capture the regulator's
right which is what we call the watchdog
issue so they
have to figure out how to hide it right
so seven offshore accounts that are hard
to penetrate or whatever it is or they
have to figure out how to pay for the
campaign budgets and pay for the
legislators that effect so they've
captured the watchdog functionally and
so typically the people who are oriented
to advance personal power are good at
finding niches to do so and so then the
question is how do we rigorously close
all those niches where those types of
behavior are never incented and that and
don't end up gaining power and the
decision-making across the space is
actually the the power of choice making
is also bound to wisdom wisdom goodness
those types of things I could talk about
this a lot like what doesn't work and
what could work and but you asked me
what's something I'm thinking about a
lot and what's something that surprised
me something that surprised me as I
started to study this was how much the
world is actually run by sociopaths and
say this in many cases within say this
just basically means sociopath is
willing to cause harm to advance their
goal but the that cause harm isn't the
goal but there are some people for whom
they have actually kind of fetishized
the exercising of their power right and
and we've certainly seen heaps of cases
of this throughout history it's it's
still true it's just generally hidden
but the book the dictators handbook is a
nice kind of intro to it there's a short
little cartoon that somebody made on
YouTube that was really good called
rules for rulers but it just explains
why it's very hard to have an
enlightened dictatorship long term
because there's so much power in that
those who are most power seeking and
willing to use the most underhanded
fucked-up techniques will try to
sure it and to not lose the position to
them you have to be able to think
through the things that they're thinking
through better and engage in some of
those tactics and so how how do you not
get beaten by warring cultures without
becoming a warring culture right and
throughout history so many of the
peaceful cultures just got slaughtered
by the warring cultures or they had to
stop being peaceful cultures so like
this this question and I used to think
more just in terms of system disposition
well it's based on the nature of what is
being incentivized and what's perverse
and sense of an externality so we need
to create real cost real value costing
and those types of things and that's
true but I was under weighting how much
there is a power-law distribution of
economic and political power we're
relatively few people have extremely
outsized capability relative to most
people and what did it take
psychologically for them to get there
and then that being there they have both
the motive and capacity to continue to
stay there and what does it take to do
that
[Music]
so these are some of the questions that
are on my mind Thank You Daniel thank
you for sharing your thoughts and just
also I think I want to say that always
present in these conversations is kind
of a way to think about our thinking to
have a little bit of a meta glimpse into
some of our habitual patterns of
thinking and easy answers
and I really appreciated about our
conversations that I walk away with more
things to think about than I had when I
started the conversation so I don't walk
away with with like oh I learned a bunch
of stuff from Daniel I use it always
walk away from these conversations with
I have a bunch of things to think about
now and I'll say to our audience here
that there's anything in this
conversation that is giving you
something to think about get a pencil on
paper or your device out and write down
that thing that it's kind of stuck with
you you know what is something that that
that you might think about
a little bit more and I would say you
know our conversations my you know as a
as a successful artist a director a
thinker you know some of the
conversations we've had have taken me
years to sort through the kinds of
questions I wrote down after a single
conversation and that to me you know
you're saying hey can you be around
somebody that that thinks differently
they do that offers you an opportunity
to upgrade your thinking or upgrade your
sense making it I says it's not just
listening to you it's actually being
willing to grapple with something you
said and I would be willing to bet that
some of things I've grappled with you
didn't even know you said to me in a
certain degree and I've taken me a long
way and and it's actually driven a lot
of growth and I think that's what that's
what we hope you know that's the
building out projects really about is
how do we help each other to to lean
away from the easy answers and lean into
the things that we have to grapple with
and and out of that there's a maybe
maybe misplaced and hopefully not
misplaced belief that we can actually
move the whole thing towards thriving
for for greater numbers of people and in
regards to your last point that we can
have people that aren't sociopaths make
a larger contribution to the world with
it can I add something to what you just
said my goal is it yeah I think people
sometimes think that learning is mostly
this process of reading or watching
something or taking in information and
it's actually mostly the grappling with
it it's mostly the digestion and
processing where it becomes your own and
the most insightful thing do you usually
get from a book wasn't written in the
book it was your own insights that came
from really contemplating and then
researching and checking it out and so
you know we all know this in learning
theory that when you start to teach
something you start to learn in a new
way because now you have to you have to
be able to explain the questions and you
have to do something with it right and
this way so often someone will read
something and they can recall a very
small percentage because it there hasn't
yet been an evolutionary impulse to say
this matters enough to remember it
because I was just reading it but when I
think about why is this relevant what
will I do with it it starts
to kind of neurologically store
differently
so in general when I'm reading I
actually read pretty slowly
because I'm reading something and then
I'm looking up references and then I'm
thinking about it and I'm relating it
with various other things that I've
known and so it's more like reading as
the center of a research process
right and the difference my friend
Jordan Hall talks about simulated
thinking versus real thinking simulated
thinking is I'm running a thought and
then I'm saying maybe it's this other
thought and I'm just running other I'm
running thoughts that have all entered
my head from some external place that's
not really thinking in right that's
basically weighing memes and deciding
which ones to propagate real thinking is
going to result oftentimes in me having
insights that I didn't intake from
anywhere and that's like what really is
the answer I don't know let's not just
pick through the ones that I've heard
let's say how would I even come to get
clear on this and what is my basis to
think through it so the beginning of
really thinking very important and even
insofar as that this so the most
important thing is that your your study
process your sense making process will
be largely mining your own sensing right
it'll take something in but then minding
your own capability as far as this
direction of just what you take in goes
because we mentioned this I just want to
share a very like simple most people
have probably heard this but not done it
yet thing that is we'll probably do more
for you than anything else we've talked
about today if you do it take the social
media apps off your phone if you keep
your social media keep it on your
computer but just don't don't have it
continuously available to hijack your
attention if you want to do art if you
want to start your thing whatever the
fuck it is don't have something that can
continuously engage your attention so
that you don't get to just be bored and
then think about the thing that you care
about so take them off your phone turn
all the notifications off on your phone
or almost all of them if you want text
or whatever term and then if you keep
social media reconfigure it where you go
through your feed and
start unfollowing everything that is not
making you a better person by seeing it
and then intentionally go find the
things you want to learn about and
follow them and make sure you're
curating dissenting views smart
dissenting views so you should be seeing
things that actually kind of bother you
but are thoughtful those couple steps
will start to help a lot yeah I can
second the turning the notifications off
on this thing and then I mean there's a
lot to say about that but there's some
really simple things that that can make
a big difference in the quality of life
at a very very short period of time so
thank you for that thank you for your
time tonight really you know like you
know I could just want to share with our
audience how much we appreciate your
your willingness to continue into the
dialogue into the conversation and even
even when it's not always there's not
even a answer to give in these questions
of being willing to give it a go and
kind of share a perspective a place that
one human being called daniel standing
in and how you see things it they think
it's that it's really invaluable and if
anything if we could be learned to begin
to stand in those places ourself and
kind of speak with some similar clarity
I think we would see some up leveling of
at least our dialogue if nothing else so
thank you for that and thank you Rachel
was really great to have this
conversation and I look forward to
talking to you again Daniel I appreciate
you all hosting these conversations and
inviting everybody and inviting me
[Music]
you